Welcome, everybody. I'm
Dr. Patricia Koyman,
and this lecture
today is on the Lower
Crost Syndrome and
Postural Considerations.
Here are the
session objectives.
First, students will be
able to appreciate the
historical background or
perspective from Hippocrates
to A.T. Still, to consideration
of the five or six
osteopathic models to Dr.
Phil Greenman's legacy and
on to the related
interprofessional and global
awareness of the lower and
upper crossed syndrome from
the legacy of neurologists,
Drs. Yanda and Lewitt.
The students will be
able to understand the
lower crossed syndrome,
including the role of the
type 1 slow twitch
postural and type 2 fast
twitch phasic muscles. The
student will understand
which muscles need
stretching and which muscles
need strengthening in
relation to application
of an understanding of
this cross syndrome.
Specific exercises will
be reviewed at the end of
the lecture with pictures
and diagrams included.
Number three, students
will be able to
understand the
importance of obtaining
and considering the
patient's history,
subjective, along with
objective information.
This objective
information can include
special tests, muscle
testing, and palpation,
the osteopathic
structural examination,
postural observation
and analysis,
and other neurological
nerve conduction
velocity or electromyography
or radiological
x-rays, MRI, etc.
testing as needed.
Number four, the students
will be able to understand
how to incorporate an
understanding of postural
compensation, tensegrity,
also known as biotensegrity,
gravitational strain
pathophysiology, GSP, and postural
decompensation into their
osteopathic perspective.
And lastly, students
will read the assigned
article from Kim. Here
is the link. This is also
listed under resources
for this classroom session
as well as in the class
preparation guide. Read
this on your own to gain
a sense of the clinical
correlation or clinical
suggestion related to
this topic area of the
lower crossed syndrome.
Okay, moving on, a brief
outline. We will go over the
historical perspective,
review muscle types one and
two, lower pelvic crossed
syndrome other postural
considerations postural
compensation tensegrity
gravitational strain
pathophysiology gsp and postural
decompensation and then
general treatment strategies
beginning with a historical
perspective from hippocrates
nearly 2500 years ago
hippocrates said the regimen
I adopt will be for the
benefit of my patients
according to my abilities
and judgment. So as we learn
about postural considerations
in osteopathic diagnosis
and treatment, we can
consider principles intended
to enhance the ability
to understand postural
mechanisms as dynamic processes
affecting interrelated
patient neuromusculoskeletal
function, and also we can
consider that with
understanding and practice, the
physician's judgment in
prescribing individualized
postural treatment regimens
will evolve and improve.
A.T. Still said, an
osteopath is only a human
engineer who should
understand all the laws
governing his engine and
thereby master disease.
Andrew Taylor still placed
much emphasis on the
fascia and its relationship
to health. He wrote,
I know of no other part
of the body that equals
the fascia as a hunting
ground in health and
disease. By its action we
live and by its failure
Here we have some
schematic drawings from the
original five models
adopted by the Educational
Council on Osteopathic
Principles in 1982.
Here to the right
we have an expanded
six models to include
bioenergetics.
if you would like more
information about this and
the the sixth model of
bioenergetics shown here with
the yellow sun image please
click on this link and
you can read that about
that in chapter 61 dynamic
strain and the bioenergetics
model from the fifth edition
of the foundations of
osteopathic medicine text.
You can also note here
that the environmental
stressors in the pink
ovals to the side are
increased in the six
model viewpoint as well
as including the
bioenergetics component.
Currently in this lecture,
we're very much focused on
this biomechanical postural
model over here to the
right but this is very much
also tied into the neurological
model in in both of these
drawings as well as the
respiratory circulatory
model as we will see but all
of them can come into play
and whether internal in
relation to the patient or
external extrinsic factors all
affecting the whole of
the patient body mind and
spirit so it can get very
complicated and sometimes we
can say we're really just
looking at the tip of the
iceberg sometimes and that
there's so much below the level
of the water that we also
need to consider but you
have to start somewhere
so we keep working we keep
trying to help our patients
and seeing what else could
there be that's going on what
else could there be so dot
d-o Doctor of Osteopathic
Medicine. The initials could
also be for dig on, that
is continue to search and
learn in your osteopathic
reasoning. Back in 1909, the
famous publisher and author
Albert Hubbard visited
the old doctor, meaning Andrew
Taylor still, and published
this 32-page book, which
helped spread the word
of osteopathy in that time,
over 100 years ago. And here
we have a quote from elbert
hubbard osteopathy is
simply the practice of common
sense and in this day and
age of course we have many
other ways to spread the
word of osteopathy and
osteopathic medicine in terms of
social media online websites
and word of mouth from
students to their families
and friends so the osteopathic
perspective and viewpoint
and treatment approaches
are being spread around
the world in many ways here
we have another quote from
dr a.t still osteopathy to
me is a very sacred science
it is sacred because it is
a healing power through
all nature so your digging
on your search may bring you
to incorporate information
and or practical approaches
which originate from other
fields of reasoning
including but not limited to
osteopathic medicine itself
neurology orthopedics physiatry
functional medicine or any
other medical specialty
or primary care field,
bioenergetics, spirituality,
metabolism, and
nutrition, or any other
components of the six
models of osteopathic
medicine, chemistry,
physics, quantum physics, or
any other basic pre
-med or advanced level
sciences, embryology,
growth and development,
etc.
So many areas where you
can include your search,
your digging on to learn
more, to incorporate,
how to help your
patient can be endless.
And maybe we're really
at the tip of the iceberg
sometimes, but doing our
best to grow and learn and
see what is the best
approach for evaluation and
treatment for your patient
with their complaints.
Here we have the late Philip
E. Greenman, D-O-F-A-A-O.
He was very much digging on
throughout his osteopathic
medicine career. And we
have a picture here of his
Greenman's works, the
collected works of Philip E.
Greenman, published by the
American Academy of Osteopathy.
Here's a quote from Dr.
Greenman. What I do know is
that when I put my hands
on a patient as part of a
comprehensive physical examination,
I begin to evolve a line
of questioning that isn't
entirely conscious. I pick
up information in my hands
that guide the questions I
next need to ask. Dr. Greenman
was a professor at Michigan
State University College
of Osteopathic medicine.
And Dr. Greenman was
also aware of the work of
Drs. Yanda and Lewitt and
the crossed syndromes.
Here we have an obituary of Dr.
Greenman. He lived
from 1928 to 2013.
And in this green
highlight, if you would like
to read that on your
own, it's describing how
he had very much a
comprehensive set of
educational materials
available to practitioners.
And he introduced students
to basic models of manual
medicine relating to
diagnosis and treatment and
guided them through a standard
screening examination,
et cetera, and had a very
comprehensive approach.
He lived around the same
era, having been born
in 1928, as Dr. Yanda,
also born in 1928. So
Vladimir Yanda was an
MD, doctor of science.
Here's a picture here of
Dr. Yanda. He had a history
of poliomyelitis as a
teenager and was wheelchair
bound for three years
after an initial
quadriplegia he was a
neurologist trained at charles
university in prague in
the 1960s in canada he did
post-doctoral work with
professor john basmagian
dr basmagian often wondered
who was teaching home
because dr yanda was quite
brilliant and they were really
learning from each other
his work in rehabilitation
included research and other
clinical activities over
many decades and with a
global influence. He was often
known as the father of the
20th century rehabilitation
movement, and his research
in clinical activities
included research into
pediatrics through geriatrics.
He also did research on
pediatric conditions as a
patient became an adult. He
did research on neurodiagnostic
testing as well as postural
neurologic disorders,
ankle conditions, obscure
****** pain, and other areas.
Overall, he had a
breadth and a depth
of research that he
was involved with.
This information came from
the article, A Tribute
to a Master of Rehabilitation,
published in 2006.
You can see here in this
citation that Dr. Greenman,
along with others, wrote
this tribute as Dr.
Yanda had a global
influence. Dr. Yanda was
the editor-in-chief
of the Czech Journal,
Rehabilitation and Physical
medicine until 2002.
And he worked with
Carl Lewitt, MD, who
was another Czech
neurologist presenting
the upper and lower
crossed syndromes.
In this picture, we can see
one of the drawings from
Dr. Yanda, labeled figure
seven here. And it says it's
one of his drawings demonstrating
postural assessment.
He emphasized the local and
global assessment as part
of a complete examination,
teaching methods that
allowed the examiner to quickly
log his or her findings.
He also emphasized that
the practitioner should
not become too restricted
in their approach
and with their drawings
and to be open to
incorporating this more
global perspective as well.
Here we have a
schematic with a seesaw
and a triangle
here in the middle
where we're trying
to find balance.
One can think of this
as a homeostasis,
another word is
homeodynamic balance.
Here we have fitness
in the middle composed
of endurance,
strength, and mobility.
On one side of this seesaw
we have postural muscles,
on the other side we have
phasic muscles and we
can take a look here on the
left we see a picture of
runners here at the Boston
Marathon so they're using
more type one tonic slow
twitch muscles for the
long endurance work postural
muscles which tend to
become facilitated shortened
and tight over here
which muscles are used we
have either short distance
or intermediate distance
sprinters type 2 phasic tend
to be more fast twitch
muscles they fatigue more
easily and they tend to
become inhibitive and weak
in this category of type
2 there is a breakdown of
type 2a the fast twitch
oxidative muscles these are
more moderate in their
fatigue rate and they're
more seen more in moderate
distances and intensities
there's also a 2b the fast
twitch glycolytic muscles
short distances high
intensity and a high and
quick fatigue rate but for
the purposes of this lecture
we will just group those
together, the short
distance and the intermediate
moderate distance and
intensities together as
globally type 1 and type 2.
Okay.
So in clinical practice,
we distinguish two muscle
types in the evaluation and
treatment. Type 1 muscles,
postural slow twitch,
as we mentioned, these
react by becoming tight
or shortened as they
become facilitated in
response to postural
imbalance, injury, or
somatic dysfunction.
Thus, it is good to know
which muscles are being
categorized as postural slow
twitch muscles. On the other
side, the type 2 group of
muscles, basic muscles,
fast twitch muscles, these
react by becoming weak
as they become inhibited.
For instance, gluteus medius
muscle, a phasic muscle, may
become reflexly inhibited
due to an associated
sacroiliac or SI joint issue.
For example, an extended
sacrum, a torsion, etc.
An SI joint issue on one
side, thus causing the
muscle to become relatively
weak on that side versus
the other side. The
muscle itself has not lost
its innate strength, but
rather is inhibited and thus
becomes weak as a result
okay so the next table
type one and we will go
over in the next slide type
two muscles in the clinical
setting type one we
said postural we said
also slow twitch becoming
facilitated and thus
shortened or tight right now
we're looking at example
two, lower cross syndrome.
So we're thinking about
anteriorly, there can
be a tight iliopsoas
muscle, and posteriorly,
there can be a tight
erector spinae muscles.
And type two,
phasic, fast twitch,
becoming inhibited and
weak. And here we look
at the lower cross
syndrome. So again,
anteriorly weak-inhibited
abdominal muscles,
and posteriorly weak
-inhibited gluteus maximus
and medius muscles.
So upper and lower,
here we focus on
lower-crossed
syndromes clinically.
For example, the work
by Vladimir Yonda, MD,
there have been
observed patterns of
muscle involvement
that had been called
the upper and lower
crossed syndromes.
Upper because it involves
the upper body and lower
because it involves the
pelvis and the lower body.
It is called crossed as
there are two lines that form
a crossover with anterior
muscles being facilitated,
tight, shortened, type 1
muscles, and posteriorly,
all on one line, call it
the facilitated or shortened
line, with type 1 muscles
being also shortened this is
in response to a muscle
imbalance similarly follow
the other cross line that goes
from anterior to posterior
and we will look at pictures
next representing the
inhibited and those weak
muscles both anteriorly and
posteriorly overall so this
is like a puzzle where you
have two lines with four
stations two anterior and
two posterior groups knowing
the four groups will give
you an understanding of
which muscles can be involved
at any one time so if the
pectoralis major is tight
in the front you do have
a cross syndrome upper for
instance you can deduce which
other muscles are involved
in a particular patient
so for the lower or pelvic
crossed syndrome here's
the cross here to the left
we see the green lines a dark
green line and a outlined
green line let's start
with the dark green line so
in this picture the patient's
looking to the side we
have a parasagittal view we're
starting posteriorly with
the tight erector spinae
muscles posteriorly and we
go follow the line anteriorly
and we also have a tight
iliopsoas muscle so on the
tight line posterior to
anterior and if we go on
the weak line the outlined
here line here we have
weak gluteus maximus and we
follow the line and we go to
weak abdominals on the other
side along that line so
here's the cross that's where
we get the crossed syndrome
of tight crossed and
weak crossed and we get the
x or the cross and we see
which muscles are involved
which we'll look at this
drawing as well lower crossed
syndrome a is the tight
line which we just saw before
a letter a tight posterior
to anterior same thing a
posterior to anterior going
that way that's the tight
line so how observe how
tight line a traverses the
lumbar erector spinae muscles
and iliopsoas neurologically
shortened iliopsoas
tissues anterior tilt the
pelvic bowl creating excessive
lumbar lordosis. So that
can be a clinical indication
and sign for you to look for
to see in your observation
what is going on with
this patient, and do they
have something like a lower
cross syndrome happening.
Alternatively, we have letter
B, the weak line. So here's B.
There's the line in this
part of the cross. Looks
like an X as well. We
saw that before, weak and
weak on this part of the
line of the cross of the
exits. This is the weak
line, the B line going here.
And we can see the weak line
connecting the
abdominals and gluteals.
Weak line B permits the
lower crossed asymmetry. Core
support is lost as the
stretch weakened rectus and
traversus abdominal muscles
are overpowered by the pull
of the strong iliopsoas
and erector spinae group so
again box a for the letter
a here again the tight line
so the tight facilitated
muscles include that iliopsoas
that if we go to the lower
extremity also rectus
femoris and the hamstrings
are tight erector spinae we
mentioned before here tensor
fasculata tfl at the side
of the thigh the thigh
adductors piriformis muscle ql
quadratus lumborum as well
as the erector spinae and
the gastroc and soleus also
tight and that's moving down
the extremity box b weak and
inhibited again we talked
we should saw that here
in the outline this part
of the cross okay we can
inhibited rectus abdominis we
see that here with a little
ptosis abdominal ptosis
here weak and inhibited
abdominals transit as well as
transversus abdominis and
the obliques all of those
abdominal musculatures right
there gluteus maximus so
Posteriorly, minimus medius,
vastus lateralis, medialis,
tibialis, anterior,
as well as the deep
to the gastrocellus
complex, that
tibialis posterior,
and to the side here, coming
around, peroneus longus.
Okay, so in this picture,
the blue circles were, in
this case, we're focusing on
the lower crossed syndrome
on both sides if we look
at the gray shaded boxes
again we have that weak line
the inhibited abdominals
weak and the inhibited
gluteus medius minimus
maximus noted here and then
here's the other line the
cross here so you see x
for a cross on this line
it's all the tight facilitated
muscles so posteriorly
here again that's the
thoracolumbar extensors ql etc
and anteriorly that rectus
femoris iliopsoas okay
again table one here
we have another drawing
anterior muscles involved
in the lower cross syndrome
good to memorize so
anterior postural muscles
remember iliopsoas rectus
femoris ad adductor
brevis okay and then the
anterior phasic muscles
for the lower cross becoming
weak rectus abdominis
weak the three vasti
muscles noted here
becoming weak tibialis
anterior also becoming weak.
Moving on, so table two,
the posterior muscles
involved in the lower
cross syndrome. Again,
good to memorize.
Posterior postural muscles.
We talked about the QL
before, QL, thoracolumbar
erector spinae muscles,
the hamstrings,
piriformis, right in
there, and the gastroxoleus
complex. All of those postural
muscles becoming tight. On
the other side of the
chart here posterior phasic
muscles so gluteus maximus
medius minimus becoming weak
so a clinical association
pronation of the subtalar
joint and lower crossed
syndrome so this pronation
of the subtalar joint and
lower cross syndrome can
be associated there can
be mechanical stress up at
the knee and the patient
may have genu valgum or genu
valgus either one hip and
lumbar spine issues they
might have a muscle imbalance
tight and facilitated
type 1 muscles versus
weak and inhibited type 2
muscles and the key is often
that gluteus medius weakness
so keeping an eye out
for that in your patient.
Here's a clinical
correlation. This is
an assigned reading
by Kim and others.
The title is The Effect of
a Yanda-Based Stretching
Program on Range of Motion,
Muscular Strength, and
Pain in Middle-Aged Women
with Self-Reported muscular
skeletal symptoms so in
this study you can see here
in table five they used a
scale a numeric rating scale
pre and post intervention
and they had the two
groups the one circled in
blue was the group known as
the stretching based on
yonda approach group s-j-a-g
stretching based on yanda
approach ja group and then
the tssg was the traditional
static stretching group
and pre and post you
can see there's quite a
significant drop in the
numeric rating scale
for the stretching based on
yanda approach group so p
less than 0.05 so significantly
different from the pre
-test. So this group, this
YANDA group, showed significant
improvement in muscle
strength and pain reduction
compared to the traditional
static stretching group.
And so a
stretching program based
on the YANDA approach
would be more effective
on self-reported
muscular skeletal
symptoms caused by posture
misalignment than a
static stretching program.
So it's an interesting
research to take a look at.
These were some of the
main findings, and that's
your assigned reading
for clinical correlation.
So beyond the lower crost
syndrome, and we had previously
discussed the upper
crost syndrome, there are
other postural considerations
that one can think of,
especially as an osteopathic
physician. position and um
to think of for your
integrated homeostatic process
sometimes people like to call
it a homeodynamic process
instead of a static process
where you can use both
terms as well this process
begins in utero and can
continues throughout growth
and the central nervous
system and the peripheral
nervous system together learn
to balance the these
postural homeostatic or
homeodynamic mechanisms. So
each person will progressively
compensate in a different
way depending in part on
his or her or their unique
intrinsic and extrinsic risk
factors. Postural
preferences and patterns will
conform within the resultant
connective tissue structure.
So neuromusculoskeletal
structures will remodel and
to reflect the functional
demands placed upon them.
Functional capability
will be limited
by a less than ideal structure.
So we have other postural
considerations here. The
tensegrity model. Where does
this name tensegrity come
from? It came from architect
Buckminster Fuller in 1929.
So the word tension plus
integrity equals tensegrity.
So here you have T-E-N
-S, tense, E-G-R-I-T-Y,
integrity, tensegrity.
This can also apply to
biological systems in
addition to architecture.
Sometimes it can be used
in the terminology of
biotensegrity or just
tensegrity. In this model,
it is recognized that
areas of hypomobile,
meaning not very mobile,
somatic dysfunction
may cause compensatory
hypermobility elsewhere.
And also hypermobility,
excuse me, in one or more
regions may affect compensatory
hypomobility elsewhere.
So fascial patterning
and musculoligamentous
tensions take on
primary importance
as the model's
connecting elements.
Other postural
considerations. Often in
your osteopathic
lab education, we've
been talking about
the planes of motion.
Coronal plane are things
like the group curves,
the type one group
curves that you often
look for and or diagnose
with your patient.
Also the sagittal
plane, hyposes and
lordoses, are they
increased or decreased?
Is it one or is it
both in certain areas?
The transverse plane,
are there rotational
preferences and the
transitional regions,
occipito-atlantil, OA,
cervicothoracic, CT,
thoracolumbar, TL,
lumbosacral, LS. So we looked
at this in terms of the
zinc patterns. So the
respiratory circulatory model
and fascial preferences of
rotation. Was there a common
compensatory pattern or
uncommon compensatory pattern
we've looked at those questions
before that's something
that you can easily check
in these four areas and
make a somatic dysfunction
even diagnosis in those regions
and noting the fascial
and myofascial preferences
as well and so not just the
transverse plane but all
of the other planes as well
can be correlated with our
osteopathic somatic dysfunction
okay continuing with
other postural considerations
we can think about gravity
and gravitational strain
pathophysiology gsp so the
signs and the symptoms there
can be changes and alterations
in postural alignment
recurrent somatic dysfunctions
lower back pain, referred
pain to the extremities,
headache, somatovisceral
effects and presentations,
fatigue, and weakness.
And this can progress to
postural decompensation. And
that happens when an
individual's functional
homeostatic or homeodynamic
mechanisms are overwhelmed, or
when the degree of
pathological change becomes
structurally incapable of
resisting gravitational force.
Okay, continuing on
with the other postural
considerations related
to gravitational strain,
pathophysiology, GSP
considerations, there can be
intrinsic factors related
to the patient, and this
can include, firstly,
their age, is there any
muscle weakness, how is
their fascial elasticity,
their bone mass,
etc.
Also, is there an altered
integrity or response
from their patient's
anti-gravity tissues.
Is there any incompetent
bony anti-gravity structures
such as a spondylolysis
or a spondylolisthesis?
Also asking, is there
poor tissue health in your
patient's tissues? There
could also be questions
related to bony asymmetry.
Is there a wedge vertebra
or asymmetry in the
hemipelvis, anything like
that? Or is the patient
having a pregnancy or
increased weight gain?
These are intrinsic factors.
Extrinsic factors can
include things like did the
patient experience a
motor vehicle accident? Is
there a history of a surgery
such as a laminectomy,
anything like that
being a macrotrauma?
Is the patient involved
in sports or high
-level competitive sports
such as gymnastics,
weightlifting, football, golf,
and there could be
microtraumas from some
of these intense sport
training procedures.
So what are the
tissue responses?
Generally, as we go through
this, we can move through
all the tissues like what
is going on in the bones
and the joints the fascia
the fascial response the
muscular response excuse me
the ligamentous response and
then the related neurovascular
and lymphatic and
visceral elements moving back
here to the skeletal arthrodial
so bones and joints we
often talk about wolf law
sometimes we call it wolf's
law where bone remodels
over time in response to
the stresses placed upon it.
When we talk about the
regional transition zones
and the fascial response,
that comes from J.
Gordon's Inc. DO and the
respiratory circulatory
model. We've learned
about that in lab as
well. Looking at the
tissue preferences of OA,
we talked about this just
a moment ago, OA, CT,
TL, and LS, occipito
-atlantol, sacricothoracic,
thoracolumbar, and lumbosacral
regions, and the preferences
of those transitional regions
in terms of the horizontal
plane and rotation
related to the fascia and
myofascial structures. And
then we move on to muscular
responses. Does the patient
have any trigger points? And
these may be related to
myotomal or sclerotermal pain
patterns. You've heard of
dermatomal pain patterns.
Myo means muscle, so
muscle-related referral
pain patterns, or
sclerotermal, relating
more to ligamentous
tissues, pain patterns.
Something to consider.
Tight versus weak muscle
patterns, that's the focus
of this lecture, but we want
to consider the whole
picture for the patient,
such as in the upper crossed
and lower focus of this
lecture, pelvic crossed
syndromes. Okay, so we can
see where this fits in in
terms of muscles and lower
crossed syndrome. But
we don't want to forget
about the fascia, myofascial,
skelet, joints, bones,
ligaments,
ligamentous response, and
then also the related neuro,
vascular, lymphatic, and
visceral elements as well.
Continuing on, other
postural considerations,
again, with
gravitational strain,
pathophysiology,
GSP considerations.
Okay, general diagnostic
considerations. The purpose
of postural diagnosis,
therefore, is to determine
where in the continuum
a given patient is and
whether the osteopathic
postural model could or
should be integrated into
that patient's health
care regimen. To this end,
the diagnostic process
should answer at least
four specific questions.
Here we go with four
questions. Number one, does
the patient's posture play
a role in the patient's
given complaint? What is
their chief complaint?
Two,
does the patient's
posture detract or limit
the patient's ability
for self-healing?
Three, does the
patient's posture present
a significant risk
factor for pain,
dysfunction, or
pathology in the future?
And lastly, four, is
the patient able to
respond positively to
a postural treatment
regimen in a time and
cost effective manner?
So considering these
questions and their answers in
relation to your patient
will give you information
about what approach you
should take to best help your
patient to have health to
move forward with their
chief complaint when they're
coming in to see you.
Other postural considerations
again, gravitational
strain pathophysiology, GSP
considerations. The postural
diagnostic approach to
answering these questions
relies heavily on observation
and palpation. It attempts
to correlate other
findings from the patient's
history and physical examination
in order to determine
if any pertinent signs or
symptoms exist. It may also
bring in radiological or
biomechanical tests to help
quantify the extent and
type of the postural change.
so postural considerations
general treatment strategies
so we want to provide
postural education to the
patient and monitor their
compliance to provide osteopathic
manipulative treatment
generally and to the
transition zones thinking about
that respiratory circulatory
model three we want to
provide some postural exercise
four if needed some static
postural bracing five
functional postural orthotics
if needed and six other
miscellaneous approaches
can be incorporated okay
symptoms compensatory or
facilitative mechanisms may
cause cervical thoracic and
lumbosacral pain there could
be also associated gastrointestinal
disorders abdominal
pain pelvic pain inguinal
pain patient can have
headache and neck pain you
can see in this ideal posture
there's less strain and
gravitational strain
pathophysiology whereas the
drawings of the two theoretical
patients to the right show
postural decompensation
Increased thoracic kyphosis,
increased lumbar lordosis,
abdominal ptosis, rounded
shoulders, head forward,
head even more forward,
even more rounded shoulders,
and even more kind of
thrusting forward in
the pelvis weakness here in
the abdominals, increased
kyphosis, so you can see
the postural strains.
okay general treatment
strategies continued overall
there are many approaches
that are used to assist the
body's postural response
to gravity an individually
designed conservative
program includes a carefully
selected combination of
patient education osteopathic
manipulative manipulative
treatment exercise and
functional orthotics when
needed all of these are aimed
at modifying the structure
function, sometimes
called form and function
relationship, and enhancing the
body's ability to self
-heal. Therefore, postural
balancing requires an
understanding of the biomechanical
nature and functional
anatomy of each patient and
a full understanding of
the osteopathic philosophy.
Patients are also awakening
to the fact that current
conventional medical
interventions are often
dangerous, costly, and
ineffective. The U.S. medical
system continues to be
the third largest cause of
death after cardiovascular
illness and cancer. To
change this long-term
trend. It is vital to employ
therapeutics that are effective,
efficient, and relatively
less expensive and
produce the least side
effects. The profession needs
to identify and treat the
root cause of illness,
be it of the body, mind,
spirit, and or the energy
fields that support them.
DOs need to develop, refine,
and use their osteopathic
skills so that they can
adhere to Dr. Still's
reminder. To find health
should be the object of the
doctor. Anyone can find
disease. And if you would
like to read more on this
topic, please click on
the link, which is also
provided in your supplemental
reading listed in your
class preparation guide,
the chapter 61 from the
current fifth edition
of the Foundations of
Osteopathic Medicine.
For the last part of the
lecture we're going to
be reviewing the lower
crossed syndrome exercises,
first stretching and
then strengthening.
And here we are, lower
crossed syndrome stretching.
So here we have a picture
of a patient doing an
iliopsoas hip flexor stretch
in the kneeling position.
A lot of these stretches
can be held for
about 30 seconds up to
one minute, 60 seconds.
It's important to have
the knee over the ankle
and not having the knee
overshoot the foot in this
position. So this is good
alignment for this patient.
They're stretching the
right side iliopsoas muscle.
Another way to do this
stretch is shown here. This is
a drawing of a patient
lying on her back, pillow
under her head. She's pulling
one knee up to her chest.
And then the side that
is being stretched is
hanging off just to
the side of the table.
Here it's actually dropping
down. This is the actual
stretch here. And this is
also for the right side
iliopsoas muscle. and in
both of these cases the
patient could turn around
shift to the other side and
stretch the other other
side as well here we have
a patient on in this left
picture holding on to the
wall she is stretching her
left side rectus femoris
muscle again holding about
30 to 60 seconds holding
her foot if it's difficult
for a patient to do that
they could put a chair
behind them balance with
their hands at the wall and
simply put their foot on
the chair and then have
a nice gentle stretch for
their rectus femoris muscle
that's a wonderful option
for patients who are just
not able to get into this
more flexible position
here they're less flexible
this is a good option
and a good workaround for
the ad adductor brevis a
groin stretch the patient
could do a wide lunge
with one knee bent one leg
straight facing forward
in that coronal plane
and then they shift a
little bit to the side and
the patient will feel a
stretch in that ad adductor
brevis area, again,
holding 30 to 60 seconds.
Here there's the patient
on a mat, like a low
bench, and they lean over
to one side, reaching
their arm to the side,
and this will stretch
their QL quadratus
lumborum for a lateral
flexion trunk stretch
in the sitting position.
This one they
mentioned, patient
could hold this for
up to two minutes.
Or the patient can
simply stand and reaching
up and over to the side.
That would be stretching
this right side, QL,
quadratus lumborum,
noted also as a lateral
flexion, trunk stretch.
Sometimes lateral flexion
we call side bending.
okay it's another term for
the same thing okay here
we have the patient on
the the table with the mat
and they're uh on lying more
in the towards the prone
position but they scooted
back towards their hips
knees are bent and reaching
their arms forward so
stretching the erector
spinae so they have a trunk
flexion motion and can
hold again 30 to 60 seconds
this one the patient flips
over they're lying on
their back in the supine
position also erector
spinae stretch hugging
both knees into their to
their chest okay this
patient is sitting at close
to the edge of a chair
one knee is bent the
other leg is straight or
it could be slightly bent
The patient's putting
both of her hands on her
bent knee. That's the
supporting knee. So her
hands on the supporting
knee, not the actual
leg that is being
stretched slightly bent.
And right here on that
left hamstring, that's
where the patient's going
to feel the stretch.
You want to avoid feeling
the stretch at the extremes,
at the sit bone, or at
the back of the knee,
because that would be more
at the tendinous insertions
of the muscle. and the
patient should really
be feeling the stretch in
the belly of the muscle.
Okay, next is the gastroc
soleus complex stretch.
The patient will have a
straight leg stretch for their
gastroc as they're standing
near a wall, holding onto
the wall for support, and
their front leg is forward.
the knee is bent more
or less knee over over
the toe over the foot
not too far over just
right in line and they're
stretching the leg
that's behind and the
heel is on the ground
okay more stretches here's
a patient a drawing of a
patient sitting in a chair
kind of halfway forward
and they sit up straight
they cross their ankle onto
their knee knee is bent
and they lean forward with
a straight back. They
try not to hunch forward
with a straight back. I
like to say like the leaning
tower of Pisa and they're
going to hold that for
about 30 to 60 seconds. They
can turn their head. They
can stay either facing
forward or turn their head
towards the direction of
the crossed leg or towards
their toes. Sometimes
they say nose to toes, but
again, they're not rounding
forward. They're just
tipping in that direction
slightly. So what I tell
patients is try all three
angles straight towards the
knee, towards the foot.
See which one gives you the
most sense of a stretch
in your piriformis muscle.
Here we have other ways
to do the piriformis
stretch besides seated
is lying on their back.
The patient could simply
put their ankle on
their knee, and they may
feel a good stretch on
that left side. The
stretch is happening on
the side of the bent knee
that is crossed over.
Here, this patient will
have a more intense stretch.
Again, the ankle is crossed
over the opposite knee.
Their hands are thread
through to hold behind the
thigh of the leg that is
free, that is not crossed
over. and they pull that
towards their chest, and
they'll feel a stretch on
that piriformis muscle,
in this case, in this
picture on the left side.
Moving on to lower cross
syndrome strengthening
exercises.
Here to the left, we have a
patient who is demonstrating
upper abdominal strengthening.
here's the starting
position and then the
patient lifts their upper and
mid back and their head off
the exercise mat and table
reaches their arms along
you know towards their
knees and they can hold the
stretch and and for a moment
and then lower down and
repeat about eight to 15
repetitions and sometimes
they can rest and then do a
second set for the lower
abdominals here's a pelvic tilt
exercise again patients
lying on their back like the
first one but now as
opposed to focusing on those
upper abdominals this will
target the lower abdominals
they roll their pelvis
just a little bit into a
pelvic tilt they can and do
this with their breathing
and exhalation as well
okay this drawing is
showing um vastus intermedius
vastus lateralis and
vastus medialis strengthening
and the patient has
a little step stool they
can step up onto the
step stool get their balance
and then lower back down
so they're working the
leg that is stepping up
And that can do 8 to 15
repetitions for that.
Alternatively,
the patient could be
standing on a step stool of
sorts with one leg, and
then they lower a straight
leg, their heel, tap, and
bring the leg back up.
So the strengthening is
actually happening on the
leg that is staying on the
stool or the step stool
as they go to tap the
other leg because this bent
leg on the stool has to
do quite a bit of work for
balance. If there's a
way to have something to
hold onto for balance, that
can be helpful as well.
And they can repeat that
as many times, eight
to 15 times if they're
able to do so. These
two drawings show a
patient who has started,
well, they don't show them
standing, but they started
standing. they kept their
back flat against the
wall and they slid down
until their legs were 90
degrees and they shifted
the weight to the heels okay
for this one we see a
patient holding on to the
the ledge of a counter and
their patient is lifting
their toes on both sides
and here's a drawing of
that holding on to something
for balance lifting the
toes showing the tibialis
anterior muscle region.
And then the
instruction would be
to repeat that
eight to 20 times.
Okay, more strengthening.
The patient can again hold
on to a treatment table
or to a counter in their
home, their kitchen
counter, and they start from
standing. And here's an
arrow. They lift their whole
leg backwards and then
they bring it back and they
can repeat that 12 to 15
times and then the other
side so gluteus maximus
hip extension while they're
standing if the patient
were to then go to actually
lie down prone on their
belly on a treatment table
they cannot do hip
extension on their stomach
again lifting their leg up
the whole leg straight up
as high as they can comfortably
again about 12 to 15 times
okay this patient is lying
on their side little support
with their arm here
supporting their head and then
lifting the straight leg up
looks like about 30 maybe
35 degrees not more than
40 degrees abduction here,
abducting the hip and the
hand is keeping them from
rolling backwards so that
they keep a good alignment
here. And again, 8 to 15
repetitions, working on that
gluteus medius and minimus
with the hip abduction.
Another exercise would be
standing. Again, there's
a little stool or elevation
that the patient can
stand on with one leg
and hands on the hands on
their iliac crests here
and she's simply letting
one side drop down and
then lifting this up so
this part where they're
lifting up is called the hip
hike and they're stabilizing
so the work is really
happening especially in
that standing leg which
has to help them to
balance and not fall off so
they're doing a lot of
work on this standing leg
and then again same thing
eight to 15 reps they can
turn around and do the other
side as well okay that's
the end of the exercises
for lower cross syndrome a
summary slide the lower pelvic
cross syndrome provides a
clear framework from which
to view a patient's postural
compensations and subsequently
target the treatment
approaches, which can include
an exercise prescription,
as we just noted in the
examples. And we went through
the stretches and
strengthening. Other postural
considerations are manifold
and important to consider in a
patient's clinical
presentation. Application of the
osteopathic perspective and
the osteopathic philosophy
can be beneficial for a
patient's overall well-being.
These are the references.
Mostly your reading, required
reading, is coming from
the Foundation's fourth
edition. All the links are
here. They're also listed in
your class preparation guide.
the new fifth edition chapter
92 has similar readings
but this fourth edition is
where your assignment is
coming from and then if
you're interested there's the
new chapter 61 in the fifth
edition dynamic strain
and the bioenergetics model
if you want to read further
in that on your own time
references for this lecture
are here not required for
you to read those except for
number eight, that one by
Kim, is the brief article.
The link is here. That
one is required that
we went over as a
clinical correlation.
Here's the lab feedback
form. Please take some
time to provide feedback.
We always try to
make lectures better
every year. Thank you so
much for your time I hope
you learned something
about the lower crossed
syndrome thank you